<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Server on go-swagger toolkit</title>
    <link>//goswagger.io/categories/server/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Server on go-swagger toolkit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016 go-swagger contributors</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 23:19:15 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//goswagger.io/categories/server/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Generate a server for a swagger spec</title>
      <link>//goswagger.io/generate/server/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 23:19:15 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//goswagger.io/generate/server/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The toolkit has a command that will let you generate a docker friendly server with support for TLS.
You can configure it through environment variables that are commonly used on PaaS services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A generated server uses &lt;em&gt;no reflection&lt;/em&gt; except for an enum validation and the required validation. The server builds all the necessary plans and execution paths at startup time so that at runtime there is only the absolute minimum processing required to respond to requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default router for go-swagger is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/naoina/denco&#34;&gt;naoina&amp;rsquo;s denco&lt;/a&gt; which is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/julienschmidt/go-http-routing-benchmark#github&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; fast&lt;/a&gt; ternary search tree based router that allows for much greater flexibility than the trie based router implementation of julienschmidt at almost the same and sometimes lower cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can provide your own router implementation should you so desire it&amp;rsquo;s abstracted through an interface with this use case in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;usage:3c3fb84840715ff4411349984ebc0a77&#34;&gt;Usage&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;swagger generate server [server-OPTIONS]

[server command options]
      -f, --spec=            the spec file to use (default: ./swagger.json)
      -a, --api-package=     the package to save the operations (default: operations)
      -m, --model-package=   the package to save the models (default: models)
      -s, --server-package=  the package to save the server specific code (default: restapi)
      -c, --client-package=  the package to save the client specific code (default: client)
      -t, --target=          the base directory for generating the files (default: ./)
      -A, --name=            the name of the application, defaults to a mangled value of info.title
      -O, --operation=       specify an operation to include, repeat for multiple
          --tags=            the tags to include, if not specified defaults to all
      -P, --principal=       the model to use for the security principal
          --default-scheme=  the default scheme for this API (default: http)
      -M, --model=           specify a model to include, repeat for multiple
          --skip-models      no models will be generated when this flag is specified
          --skip-operations  no operations will be generated when this flag is specified
          --skip-support     no supporting files will be generated when this flag is specified
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The server application gets generated with all the handlers stubbed out with a not implemented handler. That means that you can start the API server immediately after generating it. It will respond to all valid requests with 501 Not Implemented. When a request is invalid it will most likely respond with an appropriate 4xx response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generated server allows for a number of command line parameters to customize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;--host=            the IP to listen on (default: localhost) [$HOST]
--port=            the port to listen on for insecure connections, defaults to a random value [$PORT]
--tls-host=        the IP to listen on for tls, when not specified it&#39;s the same as --host [$TLS_HOST]
--tls-port=        the port to listen on for secure connections, defaults to a random value [$TLS_PORT]
--tls-certificate= the certificate to use for secure connections [$TLS_CERTIFICATE]
--tls-key=         the private key to use for secure conections [$TLS_PRIVATE_KEY]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The server takes care of a number of things when a request arrives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;routing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;input validation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;content negotiation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parameter and body binding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this with a pseudo handler, this is what happens in a request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;import (
  &amp;quot;net/http&amp;quot;

  &amp;quot;github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger/errors&amp;quot;
  &amp;quot;github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger/httpkit/middleware&amp;quot;
  &amp;quot;github.com/gorilla/context&amp;quot;
)

func newCompleteMiddleware(ctx *middleware.Context) http.Handler {
  return http.HandlerFunc(func(rw http.ResponseWriter, r *http.Request) {
    defer context.Clear(r)

    // use context to lookup routes
    if matched, ok := ctx.RouteInfo(r); ok {

      if len(matched.Authenticators) &amp;gt; 0 {
        if _, err := ctx.Authorize(r, matched); err != nil {
          ctx.Respond(rw, r, matched.Produces, matched, err)
          return
        }
      }

      bound, validation := ctx.BindAndValidate(r, matched)
      if validation != nil {
        ctx.Respond(rw, r, matched.Produces, matched, validation)
        return
      }

      result, err := matched.Handler.Handle(bound)
      if err != nil {
        ctx.Respond(rw, r, matched.Produces, matched, err)
        return
      }

      ctx.Respond(rw, r, matched.Produces, matched, result)
      return
    }

    // Not found, check if it exists in the other methods first
    if others := ctx.AllowedMethods(r); len(others) &amp;gt; 0 {
      ctx.Respond(rw, r, ctx.spec.RequiredProduces(), nil, errors.MethodNotAllowed(r.Method, others))
      return
    }
    ctx.Respond(rw, r, ctx.spec.RequiredProduces(), nil, errors.NotFound(&amp;quot;path %s was not found&amp;quot;, r.URL.Path))
  })
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to handling requests however you probably want to configure the API with some actual implementations.  To do that you have to edit the configure_xxx_api.go file.  That file will only be generated the first time you generate a server application from a swagger spec. So the generated server uses this file to let you fill in the blanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the todolist application that file looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;package main

import (
	&amp;quot;github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger/errors&amp;quot;
	&amp;quot;github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger/httpkit&amp;quot;
	&amp;quot;github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger/httpkit/middleware&amp;quot;

	&amp;quot;github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger/examples/todo-list/restapi/operations&amp;quot;
	&amp;quot;github.com/go-swagger/go-swagger/examples/todo-list/restapi/operations/todos&amp;quot;
)

// This file is safe to edit. Once it exists it will not be overwritten

func configureAPI(api *operations.ToDoListAPI) http.Handler {
	// configure the api here
	api.JSONConsumer = httpkit.JSONConsumer()

	api.JSONProducer = httpkit.JSONProducer()

	api.KeyAuth = func(token string) (interface{}, error) {
		return nil, errors.NotImplemented(&amp;quot;api key auth (key) x-petstore-token from header has not yet been implemented&amp;quot;)
	}

	api.AddOneHandler = todos.AddOneHandlerFunc(func(params todos.AddOneParams, principal interface{}) middleware.Responder {
		return middleware.NotImplemented(&amp;quot;operation addOne has not yet been implemented&amp;quot;)
	})
	api.DestroyOneHandler = todos.DestroyOneHandlerFunc(func(params todos.DestroyOneParams, principal interface{}) middleware.Responder {
		return middleware.NotImplemented(&amp;quot;operation destroyOne has not yet been implemented&amp;quot;)
	})
	api.FindHandler = todos.FindHandlerFunc(func(params todos.FindParams, principal interface{}) middleware.Responder {
		return middleware.NotImplemented(&amp;quot;operation find has not yet been implemented&amp;quot;)
	})
	api.UpdateOneHandler = todos.UpdateOneHandlerFunc(func(params todos.UpdateOneParams, principal interface{}) middleware.Responder {
		return middleware.NotImplemented(&amp;quot;operation updateOne has not yet been implemented&amp;quot;)
	})

	return setupGlobalMiddleware(api.Serve(setupMiddlewares))
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you look at the code for the configureAPI method then you&amp;rsquo;ll notice that the api object has properties for consumers.
A consumer is an object that can marshal things from a wireformat to an object.  Consumers and their counterpart producers who write objects get their names generated from the consumes and produces properties on a swagger specification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interface definitions for consumers and producers look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;// ConsumerFunc represents a function that can be used as a consumer
type ConsumerFunc func(io.Reader, interface{}) error

// Consume consumes the reader into the data parameter
func (fn ConsumerFunc) Consume(reader io.Reader, data interface{}) error {
	return fn(reader, data)
}

// Consumer implementations know how to bind the values on the provided interface to
// data provided by the request body
type Consumer interface {
	// Consume performs the binding of request values
	Consume(io.Reader, interface{}) error
}

// ProducerFunc represents a function that can be used as a producer
type ProducerFunc func(io.Writer, interface{}) error

// Produce produces the response for the provided data
func (f ProducerFunc) Produce(writer io.Writer, data interface{}) error {
	return f(writer, data)
}

// Producer implementations know how to turn the provided interface into a valid
// HTTP response
type Producer interface {
	// Produce writes to the http response
	Produce(io.Writer, interface{}) error
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s something that can turn a reader into a hydrated interface. A producer is the counterpart of a consumer and writes objects to an io.Writer.  When you configure an api with those you make sure it can marshal the types for the supported content types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing that happens in the configureAPI method is setting up the authentication with a stub handler in this case. This particular swagger specification supports token based authentication and as such it wants you to configure a token auth handler.  Any error for an authentication handler is assumed to be an invalid authentication and will return the 401 status code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;// UserPassAuthentication authentication function
type UserPassAuthentication func(string, string) (interface{}, error)

// TokenAuthentication authentication function
type TokenAuthentication func(string) (interface{}, error)

// AuthenticatorFunc turns a function into an authenticator
type AuthenticatorFunc func(interface{}) (bool, interface{}, error)

// Authenticate authenticates the request with the provided data
func (f AuthenticatorFunc) Authenticate(params interface{}) (bool, interface{}, error) {
	return f(params)
}

// Authenticator represents an authentication strategy
// implementations of Authenticator know how to authenticate the
// request data and translate that into a valid principal object or an error
type Authenticator interface {
	Authenticate(interface{}) (bool, interface{}, error)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we finally get to configuring our route handlers. For each operation there exists an interface so that implementations have some freedom to provide alternative implentations. For example mocks in certain tests, automatic stubbing handlers, not implemented handlers. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the addOne handler in a bit more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;// AddOneHandlerFunc turns a function with the right signature into a add one handler
type AddOneHandlerFunc func(AddOneParams, interface{}) middleware.Responder

// Handle executing the request and returning a response
func (fn AddOneHandlerFunc) Handle(params AddOneParams, principal interface{}) middleware.Responder {
	return fn(params, principal)
}

// AddOneHandler interface for that can handle valid add one params
type AddOneHandler interface {
	Handle(AddOneParams, interface{}) middleware.Responder
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the &lt;code&gt;addOne&lt;/code&gt; operation requires authentication, this interface definition requires 2 arguments. The first argument is about the request parameters and the second parameter is the security principal for the request.  In this case it is of type &lt;code&gt;interface{}&lt;/code&gt;, typically that is a type like Account, User, Session, &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is your job to provide such a handler. Go swagger guarantees that by the time the request processing ends up at the handler, the parameters and security principal have been bound and validated.  So you can safely proceed with saving the request body to some persistence medium perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a context that gets created where the handlers get wired up into a &lt;code&gt;http.Handler&lt;/code&gt;. For the add one this looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;// NewAddOne creates a new http.Handler for the add one operation
func NewAddOne(ctx *middleware.Context, handler AddOneHandler) *AddOne {
	return &amp;amp;AddOne{Context: ctx, Handler: handler}
}

/*AddOne swagger:route POST / todos addOne

AddOne add one API

*/
type AddOne struct {
	Context *middleware.Context
	Params  AddOneParams
	Handler AddOneHandler
}

func (o *AddOne) ServeHTTP(rw http.ResponseWriter, r *http.Request) {
	route, _ := o.Context.RouteInfo(r)

	uprinc, err := o.Context.Authorize(r, route)
	if err != nil {
		o.Context.Respond(rw, r, route.Produces, route, err)
		return
	}
	var principal interface{}
	if uprinc != nil {
		principal = uprinc
	}

	if err := o.Context.BindValidRequest(r, route, &amp;amp;o.Params); err != nil { // bind params
		o.Context.Respond(rw, r, route.Produces, route, err)
		return
	}

	res := o.Handler.Handle(o.Params, principal) // actually handle the request

	o.Context.Respond(rw, r, route.Produces, route, res)

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;http.Handler&lt;/code&gt; implementation takes care of authentication, binding, user code execution and generating a response. For authentication this request would end up in the &lt;code&gt;TokenAuthentication&lt;/code&gt; handler that was put on the api context object earlier.  When a request is authenticated it gets bound. This operation eventually requires an object that is an implementation of &lt;code&gt;RequestBinder&lt;/code&gt;.  The &lt;code&gt;AddOneParams&lt;/code&gt; are such an implementation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;// RequestBinder is an interface for types to implement
// when they want to be able to bind from a request
type RequestBinder interface {
	BindRequest(*http.Request, *MatchedRoute) error
}

// AddOneParams contains all the bound params for the add one operation
// typically these are obtained from a http.Request
//
// swagger:parameters addOne
type AddOneParams struct {
	/*
	  In: body
	*/
	Body *models.Item
}

// BindRequest both binds and validates a request, it assumes that complex things implement a Validatable(strfmt.Registry) error interface
// for simple values it will use straight method calls
func (o *AddOneParams) BindRequest(r *http.Request, route *middleware.MatchedRoute) error {
	var res []error

	var body models.Item
	if err := route.Consumer.Consume(r.Body, &amp;amp;body); err != nil {
		res = append(res, errors.NewParseError(&amp;quot;body&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;body&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&amp;quot;, err))
	} else {
		if err := body.Validate(route.Formats); err != nil {
			res = append(res, err)
		}

		if len(res) == 0 {
			o.Body = &amp;amp;body
		}
	}

	if len(res) &amp;gt; 0 {
		return errors.CompositeValidationError(res...)
	}
	return nil
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example there is only a body parameter, so we make use of the selected consumer to read the request body and turn it into an instance of models.Item. When the body parameter is bound, it gets validated and when validation passes no error is returned and the body property is set.  After a request is bound and validated the parameters and security principal are passed to the request handler. For this configuration that would return a 501 responder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go swagger uses responders which are an interface implementation for things that can write to a response. For the generated server there are status code response and a default response object generated for every entry in the spec. For the &lt;code&gt;addOne&lt;/code&gt; operation that are 2 objects one for the success case (201) and one for an error (default).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;// Responder is an interface for types to implement
// when they want to be considered for writing HTTP responses
type Responder interface {
	WriteResponse(http.ResponseWriter, httpkit.Producer)
}

/*AddOneCreated Created

swagger:response addOneCreated
*/
type AddOneCreated struct {

	// In: body
	Payload *models.Item `json:&amp;quot;body,omitempty&amp;quot;`
}

// WriteResponse to the client
func (o *AddOneCreated) WriteResponse(rw http.ResponseWriter, producer httpkit.Producer) {

	rw.WriteHeader(201)
	if o.Payload != nil {
		if err := producer.Produce(rw, o.Payload); err != nil {
			panic(err) // let the recovery middleware deal with this
		}
	}
}

/*AddOneDefault error

swagger:response addOneDefault
*/
type AddOneDefault struct {

	// In: body
	Payload *models.Error `json:&amp;quot;body,omitempty&amp;quot;`
}

// WriteResponse to the client
func (o *AddOneDefault) WriteResponse(rw http.ResponseWriter, producer httpkit.Producer) {

	rw.WriteHeader(500)
	if o.Payload != nil {
		if err := producer.Produce(rw, o.Payload); err != nil {
			panic(err) // let the recovery middleware deal with this
		}
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So an implementer of the &lt;code&gt;AddOneHandler&lt;/code&gt; could return one of these 2 objects and go-swagger is able to respect the contract set forward by the spec document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to implement the AddOneHandler you could do something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;todos.AddOneHandlerFunc(func(params todos.AddOneParams, principal interface{}) middleware.Responder {
  created, err := database.Save(params.Body)
  if err != nil {
    return AddOneDefault{models.Error{500, err.Error()}}
  }
  return AddOneCreated{created}
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use the generated server</title>
      <link>//goswagger.io/use/server/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2015 07:44:06 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//goswagger.io/use/server/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The generated server serves the API but the default implementation returns 501 Not implemented for everything. Let&amp;rsquo;s
look into using the generated code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go swagger primarily deals with HTTP and originally only supports the stdlib &lt;code&gt;net/http&lt;/code&gt; interface. A typical HTTP
request expects a response.  This is reflected in go-swagger where a handler is typically defined as a function of
input parameters to a responder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;type ListTravelsHandler interface {
	Handle(ListTravelsParams) middleware.Responder
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signature of this handler is one of 2 possible variations. When a handler doesn&amp;rsquo;t use authentication then a handler
interface consists out of input parameters and a responder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;type AddOneAuthenticatedHandler interface {
	Handle(AddOneParams, interface{}) middleware.Responder
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a handler does use authentication then the second argument to the handler function represents the security
principal for your application. You can specify the type name for this principal at generation time by specifying the
-P or &amp;ndash;principal flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;swagger generate server -P models.User
swagger generate client -P models.User
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you would execute the generate step with that parameter for the security principal then the
AddOneAuthenticatedHandler would look a bit like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;type AddOneAuthenticatedHandler interface {
	Handle(AddOneParams, *models.User) middleware.Responder
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;implement-handlers:3c3fb84840715ff4411349984ebc0a77&#34;&gt;Implement handlers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A handler is an interface/contract that defines a statically typed representation of the input and output parameters of
an operation on your API.
The tool generates handlers that are stubbed with a NotImplemented response when you first generate the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-not-implemented-handler:3c3fb84840715ff4411349984ebc0a77&#34;&gt;The not implemented handler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The not implemented handler is actually a not implemented responder, it returns a responder that will always respond
with status code 501 and a message that lets people know it&amp;rsquo;s not the fault of the client that things don&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;middleware.NotImplemented(&amp;quot;operation todos.AddOne has not yet been implemented&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;your-own-code:3c3fb84840715ff4411349984ebc0a77&#34;&gt;Your own code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each HTTP request expects a response of some sort, this response might have no data but it&amp;rsquo;s a response none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every incoming request is described as a bunch of input parameters which have been validated prior to calling the
handler. So whenever your code is executed, the input parameters are guaranteed to be valid according to what the
swagger specification prescribes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the input parameters have been validated, and the request has been authenticated should it have triggered
authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably want to return something a bit more useful to the users of your API than a not implemented response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible implementation of the &lt;code&gt;ListTravelsHandler&lt;/code&gt; interface might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;type PublicListTravelsOK struct {
  Body []models.Travel
}
func (m *PublicListTravelsOK) WriteResponse(rw http.ResponseWriter, producer httpkit.Producer){
  // generated code here
}

type PublicListTravelsError struct {
  Body models.Error
}
func (m *PublicListTravelsOK) WriteResponse(rw http.ResponseWriter, producer httpkit.Producer){
  // generated code here
}

type PublicListTravelsHandler struct {
  db interface {
    FetchTravels(*PublicListTravelsParams) ([]models.Travel, error)
  }
}

func (m *PublicListTravelsHandler) Handle(params ListTravelsParams) middleware.Responder {
  travels, err := m.db.FetchTravels(&amp;amp;params)
  if err != nil {
    return &amp;amp;PublicListTravelsError{Body: models.Error{Message: err.Error()}}
  }
  return &amp;amp;PublicListTravelsOK{Body: travels}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example above we have a handler implementation with a hypothetical database fetch interface. When the handle
method is executed there are 2 possible responses for the provided parameters. There can either be an error in which
case the PublicListTravelsError will be returned, otherwise the PublicListTravelsOK will be returned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code generator has written the remaining code to render that response with the headers etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BYO middleware</title>
      <link>//goswagger.io/use/middleware/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 15:39:37 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//goswagger.io/use/middleware/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Go-swagger chose the golang &lt;code&gt;net/http&lt;/code&gt; package as base abstraction. That means that for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; supported transport by the toolkit you can reuse &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; middleware existing middlewares that following the stdlib middlware pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several projects providing middleware libraries for weaving all kinds of functionality into your request handling. None of those things are the job of go-swagger, go-swagger just serves your specs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The server takes care of a number of things when a request arrives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;routing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;input validation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;content negotiation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parameter and body binding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re unfamiliar with the concept of golang net/http middlewares you can read up on it here:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alexedwards.net/blog/making-and-using-middleware&#34;&gt;Making and Using HTTP Middleware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides serving the swagger specification as an API, the toolkit also serves the actual swagger specification document.
The convention is to use the &lt;code&gt;/swagger.json&lt;/code&gt; location for serving up the specification document, so we serve the
specification at that path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;add-middleware:37ab2f15ff048f67959bcac0a6032f32&#34;&gt;Add middleware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generated server allows for 2 extension points to inject middleware in its middlware chain. These have to do with
the lifecycle of a request. You can find those hooks in the configure_xxx_api.go file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is to add middleware all the way to the top of the middleware stack. To do this you add them in the
&lt;code&gt;setupGlobalMiddleware&lt;/code&gt; method. This middleware applies to everything in the go-swagger managed API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func setupGlobalMiddleware(handler http.Handler) http.Handler {
	return handler
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second extension point allows for middleware to be injected right before actually handling a matched request.
This excludes the swagger.json document from being affected by this middlware though.  This extension point makes the
middlewares execute right after routing but right before authentication, binding and validation.  You add middlewares
to this point by editing the &lt;code&gt;setupMiddlewares&lt;/code&gt; method in configure_xxx_api.go&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func setupMiddlewares(handler http.Handler) http.Handler {
	return handler
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global middleware is an excellent place to do things like panic handling, request logging or adding metrics.  While
the plain middleware allows you to kind of filter this by request path without having to take care of routing. You also
get access to the full context that the go-swagger toolkit uses throughout the lifecycle of a request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;add-logging-and-panic-handling:37ab2f15ff048f67959bcac0a6032f32&#34;&gt;Add logging and panic handling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very common requirement for HTTP API&amp;rsquo;s is to include some form of logging. Another one is to handle panics from your
API requests.  The example for a possible implementation of this uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dre1080/recover&#34;&gt;this community provided
middleware&lt;/a&gt; to catch panics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func setupGlobalMiddleware(handler http.Handler) http.Handler {
  recovery := recover.New(&amp;amp;recover.Options{
    Log: log.Print,
  })
  return recovery(handler)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tons of middlewares out there, some are framework specific and some frameworks don&amp;rsquo;t really use the plain
vanilla golang net/http as base abstraction. For those you can use a project like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/carbocation/interpose&#34;&gt;interpose&lt;/a&gt; that serves as an adapter
layer so you can still reuse middlewares. Of course nobody is stopping you to just implement your own middlewares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example using interpose to integrate with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/carbocation/interpose/blob/master/middleware/negronilogrus.go&#34;&gt;logrus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;import (
  interpose &amp;quot;github.com/carbocation/interpose/middleware&amp;quot;
)
func setupGlobalMiddleware(handler http.Handler) http.Handler {
  logViaLogrus := interpose.NegroniLogrus()
  return logViaLogrus(handler)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you can compose these middlewares into a stack using functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func setupGlobalMiddleware(handler http.Handler) http.Handler {
  handlePanic := recover.New(&amp;amp;recover.Options{
    Log: log.Print,
  })

  logViaLogrus := interpose.NegroniLogrus()

  return handlePanic(
    logViaLogrus(
      handler
    )
  )
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;add-rate-limiting:37ab2f15ff048f67959bcac0a6032f32&#34;&gt;Add rate limiting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also add rate limiting in a similar way. Lets say we just want to rate limit the valid requests to our swagger
API. To do so we could use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/didip/tollbooth&#34;&gt;tollbooth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func setupMiddlewares(handler http.Handler) http.Handler {
  limiter := tollbooth.NewLimiter(1, time.Second)
  limiter.IPLookups = []string{&amp;quot;RemoteAddr&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;X-Forwarded-For&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;X-Real-IP&amp;quot;}
	return tollbooth.LimitFuncHandler(handler)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with this you&amp;rsquo;ve added rate limitting to your application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Untyped API server</title>
      <link>//goswagger.io/untyped/server/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 23:21:52 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//goswagger.io/untyped/server/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The toolkit supports serving a swagger spec with untyped data. This means that it uses mostly interface{} as params to each operation and as result type. It does allow you to serve a spec up quickly. This is one of the building blocks required to serve up stub API&amp;rsquo;s and to generate a test server with predictable responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this document we&amp;rsquo;ll use the todo list application to build a server that doesn&amp;rsquo;t use any code generation. So we&amp;rsquo;ll load a predefined swagger specification document and serve it up, while writing a minimal amount of code and try to avoid requiring a type cast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>